Isabel Gordon Carter Collection
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
Guides to the Collections in the Archive of Folk Culture
Isabel Gordon Carter Collection 1921-1942
AFC 2005/004
Isabel Gordon Carter, 1897-
132 leaves.
2 photographic prints: black and white; 3 1⁄2 x 5 1⁄2 in.
1 photographic print: color; 15 x 18 in.
Archive of Folk Culture, American Folklife Center, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Collection of correspondence, notes, and photographs related to Isabel Gordon Carter's research and publications on Appalachian ballads and folktales, and customs from 1921 to 1942.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Bean, Robert Bennett, 1874-1944--Correspondence.; Bishop, E. A.--Correspondence.; Brooks, Nelly L.--Correspondence.; Carter, Isabel Gordon, 1897-; Carter, Isabel Gordon, 1897- --Correspondence.; Chase, Richard, 1904-1988--Correspondence.; Hrdlička, Aleš, 1869-1943--Correspondence.; Kephart, Horace, 1862-1931--Correspondence.; Long, Maud, 1893-1984--Correspondence.; Powell, Hannah J.--Correspondence.; Stearns, I. K.--Correspondence.; Williams-Ellis, Amabel, 1894-1984--Correspondence.
Subjects
Ballads, English--Appalachian Region--Texts.; Folk songs--Appalachian Region--Texts.; Folklore--Appalachian Region.; Jack tales--Appalachian Region.; Tales--Appalachian Region.
Titles
I'm as free a little bird as I can be.; Jonah and the whale.; Little mohea.
Form/Genre
Correspondence.; Manuscripts.; Photographic prints.
Arrangement
Organized into the following series: I. Manuscripts; II. Graphic Materials.
Acquisition
Janet Carter, daughter of Isabel Gordon Carter, donated the collection to the Archive of Folk Culture in January 2005, from the estate of her mother.
Access and Restrictions
Collection is open for research. The material is fragile. Preservation copies are available for extremely fragile items. To request materials, please contact the Folklife Reading Room at http://hdl.loc.gov/loc.afc/folklife.contact
Publications
Carter, Isabel Gordon. 1925. "Mountain White Folk-Lore: Tales from the Southern Blue Ridge." Journal of American Folklore, 38:340-374.
Biographical Notes
Isabel Gordon Carter was a collector of folktales, ballads, and riddles in North Carolina and Tennessee in the 1920s and 1930s. In the summer of 1923, Isabel Gordon Carter collected tales in the Blue Ridge region and published "Mountain White Folk-Lore: Tales from the Southern Blue Ridge" in the Journal of American Folklore in 1925. Her special interest was the traditions of mountain folk. She published numerous articles in the Southern Folklore Quarterly regarding her fieldwork and was also a social worker who wrote on aspects of social welfare. She received her M.A. from the University of Tennessee and Ph.D. from Columbia University.
Scope and Content
Collection of correspondence, notes, a research notebook, and photographs related to Isabel Gordon Carter's research and publications on Appalachian ballads, folktales, and customs from 1921 to 1942. Carter's correspondents include E. A. Bishop, Horace Kephart, I. K. Stearns, Nelly L. Brooks, Amabel Williams-Ellis, Ales Hrdlicka, Richard Chase, Kay Chase, Maud Gentry Long, Robert B. Bean, Maude Minish, Helen Dashiell, W. H. Rothe, Rev. Hannah J. Powell, and Mary H. Brown. E. A. Bishop enclosed texts for two ballads, "Jonah and the whale," and "Little Mohea" (1921) and Nelly L. Brooks sent the text to "I'm as free a little bird as I can be" (1924). Includes copies of Richard Chase's articles on Jack tales.
Photographs include Bob DeHart family in front of their cabin near Bryson City, North Carolina, and a photograph of camp equipment and car belonging to Horace Kephart, taken by I. K. Stearns, circa 1923. Also includes color photograph of an oil portrait by artist Katherine Wiley of Isabel Gordon Carter, dated 1913.
Collection Concordance by Format
Series I: Manuscripts
32 manuscript items, 132 leaves Box 1 MS01-MS32
Series II: Graphic Materials
2 black-and-white photographs Box 1 PH01-PH02
1 digital color print RR Map Case GR01
Container List
- Series I: Manuscripts
  - Finding Aid., 7 leaves. (Folder 1)
  - MS01 [MS01a-MS01e]., 5 leaves. (Folder 2)
    - MS01a. Envelope addressed to "Miss Gordon"; Elgin State Hospital; Elgin, Ill. Sent from Murphy College; Sevierville, Tenn. December 27, 1921 (postmark).
    - MS01b. Letter to "Miss Gordon" from E. A. Bishop of Murphy College referring to "two ballads." December 24, 1921.
    - MS01c. Typewritten page of "Jonah and the Whale Ballad." Undated.
    - MS01d. Typewritten page of "Little Mohea." Undated.
    - MS01e. Handwritten note with H. E. Bishop's address. Undated.
  - MS02., 1 leaf. (Folder 3)
    - MS02. Letter to "Miss Gordon" from Horace Kephart with information about vocabulary usage. August 8, 1923., 1 leaf.
  - MS03 [MS03a-MS03h]., 5 leaves. (Folder 4)
    - MS03a. Envelope addressed to "Miss Isabel Gordon"; 1616 W. Clinch Ave.; Knoxville, Tenn. Sent from Bryson City Pump Works Co.; Bryson City, N.C. September 20, 1923 (postmark).
    - MS03b. Letter to "Miss Gordon" from I. K. Stearns regarding enclosed typewritten contents and photographs (first page). September 5, 1923.
    - MS03c. Letter to "Miss Gordon" from I. K. Stearns regarding the enclosed typewritten contents and photographs (second page). September 5, 1923.
    - MS03d. Typewritten page from "Piercevill Ga" from "Wm Payne." January 13, 1902.
    - MS03e. Typewritten page from "Piercvill Ga" from "Wm Payne" (first page). March 25, 1903.
    - MS03f. Typewritten page from "Piercvill Ga" from "Wm Payne" (second page). March 25, 1903.
    - MS03g. Typewritten page of an article that was copied from the Bryson City Times. November 18, 1922.
    - MS03h. Typewritten page of a notice that was posted on the door of the Alarka Lumber Company's Commissary near Bryson City, N.C. August 23, 1921.
  - MS04 [MS04a-MS04b]., 2 leaves. (Folder 5)
    - MS04a. Letter to Isabel Gordon Carter from Nelly L. Brooks (two sided). April 26, 1924.
    - MS04b. Handwritten note in Isabel Gordon Carter's handwriting noting that she collected folklore from the Brooks family when she was in Rugby, Tenn. Undated.
  - MS05. Letter to Isabel Gordon Carter from Ales Hrdlicka at the Smithsonian Institution. September 4, 1931., 1 leaf. (Folder 6)
  - MS06. Letter to Isabel Gordon Carter from Amabel Williams-Ellis requesting permission to use stories in a book she is publishing. Isabel Gordon Carter's handwritten notes in pencil on verso (two sided). May 22, 1933., 1 leaf. (Folder 7)
  - MS07. Letter to Isabel Gordon Carter from Amabel Williams-Ellis thanking her for permission to use the stories in the book she is publishing. June 27, 1933., 1 leaf. (Folder 8)
  - MS08 [MS08a-MS08b]., 2 leaves. (Folder 9)
    - MS08a. Letter to Richard Chase from Isabel Gordon Carter regarding her interest in collecting stories and the origins of her interest (first page). November 26, 1938.
    - MS08b. Letter to Richard Chase from Isabel Gordon Carter regarding her interest in collecting stories and the origins of her interest (second page). November 26, 1938.
  - MS09. Letter to Mrs. Grover Long from Isabel Gordon Carter regarding articles Gordon Carter printed and the summer of 1923 when she collected stories with the Long family. December 5, 1938., 1 leaf. (Folder 10)
  - MS10. Letter to Isabel Gordon Carter from Maud Gentry Long referring to the inquiry Gordon Carter made in MS09 (two sided). December 11, 1938., 1 leaf. (Folder 11)
  - MS11. Letter to Richard Chase from Isabel Gordon Carter regarding a trip to Richmond, Virginia. April 17, 1939., 1 leaf. (Folder 12)
  - MS12. Typewritten bulletin from Richard Chase as the Virginia Representative of the English Folk Dance & Song Society of America (two sided). January 1940., 1 leaf. (Folder 13)
  - MS13. Letter to Isabel Gordon Carter from Mrs. Richard Chase (Kay) regarding a recent household move and a borrowed book (two sided). January 24, 1940., 1 leaf. (Folder 14)
  - MS14. Letter to Isabel Gordon Carter from Richard Chase regarding "The Jack Tales" (two sided). May 16, 1940., 1 leaf. (Folder 15)
  - MS15. Reprint from Southern Folklore Quarterly, Vol. 2, No. 3, 145-147, "Jack's Hunting Trip" by Richard Chase. September 1938., 2 leaves. (Folder 16)
  - MS16. Postcard to Isabel Gordon Carter from Richard Chase regarding the printing of "The Jack Tales" (two sided). August 10, 1942., 1 leaf. (Folder 17)
  - MS17. Letter to Isabel Gordon Carter from Robert Bennett Bean. Undated., 1 leaf. (Folder 18)
  - MS18. Typewritten page with two stanzas. Undated., 1 leaf. (Folder 19)
  - MS19. Typewritten page on letterhead from 2039 New Hampshire Avenue, N.W.; Washington, D.C. 20009 September 4, 1931., 1 leaf. (Folder 20)
  - MS20 [MS20a-MS20b, FRAGILE]., 2 leaves. (Folder 21)
    - MS20a. Handwritten notes on fragile folded pages. The verso of the letter appears to be Isabel Gordon Carter's handwritten verses of "Noah just don't know..." (first page, two sided). Undated.
    - MS20b. Handwritten notes on fragile folded pages. The verso of the letter appears to be Isabel Gordon Carter's handwritten verses of "Noah just don't know..." (second page, two sided). Undated.
  - MS21. Handwritten research and field notebook. Undated., 71 leaves. (Folder 22)
  - MS22. Handwritten notes about "Butler." Undated., 10 leaves. (Folder 23)
  - MS23. Handwritten notes about gardening. June 26?, 1 leaf. (Folder 24)
  - MS24. Letter from Isabel Gordon Carter to Miss Maude Minish explaining her interest in folk tales of Tennessee and North Carolina. June 29, 1923., 1 leaf. (Folder 25)
  - MS25. Letter and envelope from Helen Dashiell to Isabel Gordon Carter. July 29, 1923., 2 leaves. (Folder 26)
  - MS26. Letter with a Junior League of America heading and a note about $5.00 dues. August 4, 1923., 2 leaves. (Folder 27)
  - MS27. Letter and clipping from W. H. Rothe to Isabel Gordon Carter. August 5, 1923., 3 leaves. (Folder 28)
- Series II: Graphic Images
  - PH01. Photograph of Bob DeHart family in front of their cabin near Bryson City, North Carolina. Stearns refers to the photograph in MS03b. Undated. (Folder 4)
  - PH02. Photograph of camp equipment and car belonging to Horace Kephart, taken by I. K. Stearns, ca. 1923. Stearns refers to the photograph in MS03c. Undated. (Folder 4)
  - GR01. Preservation copy of digital color photographic print of an oil painting portrait of Isabel Gordon Carter by Katherine Wiley. 1913. [Located in the Folklife Reading Room Map Case] (Drawer Map Case)